### **CALVIN A. ACKLEY**

4600 Silver Hill Rd. Suitland, MD 20746 Phone: (860) 823-7909

Personal Email: ackleycb@gmail.com Work Email: Calvin.Ackley@bea.gov

Web site: ackleycb.github.io

# **Summary of Qualifications**

I am a Ph.D. health economist with 10 years of experience working with large health claims databases from commercial insurers, Medicare, and Medicaid to study health care costs, quality, and utilization. I am currently a research economist at the Bureau of Economic Analysis (BEA) where I conduct research to improve the BEA's health accounts and statistics. My most recent project uses two of the largest available sources of commercial health claims to estimate regional price levels for medical care in the U.S.

I am an expert in applied statistics and empirical methods for program evaluation, causal inference, health economics and outcomes research, and choice analysis, and I am highly skilled in statistical programming with R, SAS, SQL, and STATA. My research has been published in top peer-reviewed journals in economics and health services research.

# **EDUCATION**

Ph.D., Economics, Boston University, 2020

Dissertation Title: Optimal Insurance Design and the Demand for Medical Care

Main advisor: Randall P. Ellis

B.A., Economics, Summa Cum Laude, Boston College, 2014

# **PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS**

Research Economist U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis 2020-present

Key Responsibilities:

- Work to produce and improve BEA's health care satellite account, which measures national spending by disease using data from commercial insurers, Medicare, and Medicaid.

- Research to develop regional price level estimates for medical care in the U.S. This project uses commercial claims data from the Health Care Cost Institute and the Merative MarketScan databases to measure regional variation in health care prices by type of service.
- Research to develop quality adjusted price indices and measure productivity for the health care sector. Work in this area involves using Medicare claims data, cost report data, AHRQ risk-adjustment algorithms, and CMS readmission algorithms to measure trends in costs and outcomes for a suite of acute conditions.
- Conduct independent research in applied microeconomics and health economics. Some projects include: (1) measuring changes in health care utilization as Medicaid beneficiaries transition to Medicare+Medicaid dual eligibility, (2) studying the impact of tiered cost sharing designs on spending and prices, and (3) examining the role of referring providers and vertical integration in determining site of care.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

Regional Price Level Estimates for Medical Services in the United States Forthcoming in *Health Services Research* 

Determinants of Low-Cost Provider Use: Evidence from Lab Tests Forthcoming in *Medical Care Research and Review* 

The Impact of Preferred Provider Incentives on Demand and Negotiated Prices Forthcoming in *American Journal of Health Economics* 

Tiered Cost Sharing and Health Care Demand

Journal of Health Economics Volume 85, September 2022

County-level Estimates of Excess Mortality Associated with COVID-19 in the United States (with Dielle J. Lundberg, Lei Ma, Irma T. Elo, Samuel H. Preston, and Andrew C. Stokes) *Social Science and Medicine - Population Health* Volume 17, March 2022

### WORKING PAPERS

Are Medicaid and Medicare patients treated equally? (With Abe Dunn, Eli Liebman, and Adam Shapiro)

Revise and Resubmit at American Economic Journal: Economic Policy

Changes in Lifetime Spending and Health-Adjusted Life-Expectancy, 1996 to 2016 (with Esha Dwibedi, Abe Dunn, Lasanthi Fernando, Jonah Joffe, Justine Mallatt, Chris JL Murray, Joseph L Dieleman, and Marcia R. Weaver)

Revise and Resubmit at Value in Health

#### **WORK IN PROGRESS**

Medicaid Enrollee and Provider Responses to the ACA Fee Bump: Leveraging MAX Data (with Justine Mallatt)

Quantifying Productivity Growth in Medical Care Based on Acute Conditions: Differential Trends Across the Population (with Abe Dunn and John Romley)

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Instructor, Introductory Macroeconomic Analysis, Department of Economics, Boston University, Summer 2016 and Summer 2018

Lead Teaching Fellow, Introductory Microeconomic Analysis, Department of Economics, Boston University, Fall 2018

Lead Teaching Fellow, Introductory Macroeconomic Analysis, Department of Economics, Boston University, Spring 2018

Teaching Fellow, Behavioral Economics, Department of Economics, Boston University, Fall 2017

Teaching Fellow, Introductory Microeconomic Analysis, Department of Economics, Boston University, Fall 2015-2017, Spring 2016-2017

#### **PROGRAMMING SKILLS:**

R, SAS, STATA, SQL, Shiny for dashboard development

#### **ADDITIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE**

Analyst Intern, Charles River Associates, Summer 2013

#### **PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES**

Officer, Graduate Economics Association, Boston University, 2016-2017

Referee Service: Journal of Health Economics, American Journal of Health Economics, Health Services Research

# FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

Outstanding Teaching Fellow Award, Boston University, 2016-2017

Teaching Fellowship, Boston University, 2015-2018

Dean's Fellowship, Boston University, 2014-2015

# **ADDITIONAL CERTIFICATIONS**

Cicerone Certified Beer Server